So people who are familiar with the hillside\h
hermitage teachings will likely have heard the\h\h
word 'context' used with reference to the practice.\h
So can we go over what exactly that context is\h\h
and is it something one finds already there\h
or is it something one needs to cultivate?
The context is definitely not\h
something that you fabricate.
It's not an idea that...
There is a\h
component of let's say intellectual reflection to it,
but it would be more accurate to see\h
it at the level of an emotional perspective\h\h
or an emotional attitude, rather than just an idea
that you can kind of keep at the back of your mind.
So in the most practical sense, you\hcould say
the context refers to your present state of mind.\h\h
That is the context that underlies your\h
actions and that even if you ignore it, it's still there,\h\h
which is an important thing to understand.\h
It's not that you're doing the context necessarily\hconsciously,
but you're certainly responsible\h
for cultivating the context by acting out of\hstates of
let's say greed or aversion that might\hbe there.
Even if you're not saying to yourself\h\h
"I shall act out of this context and cultivate\h
this context", through your actions coming out of\h\h
that state of mind, that is the context that you\h
are increasing and strengthening.\h
So that's why the suttas would say that somebody who...
they\hwould describe it as "giving attention\h\h
to the sign of gratification" or "the theme of\h
gratification" that when somebody does that,
their sensual desire increases. So it's not necessarily\h
that you tell yourself "I shall cultivate\h\h
the context of sensuality being pleasant and\h
agreeable". Your mind has that context already\h\h
of finding pleasure in these things and then by\h
you acting out of it you make it worse.
You make it even more easy for your mind to focus on\h
the pleasant aspect of sensuality and overlook the danger.
So there is a right context and a\h
wrong context. Exactly. So then in a way it's\h\h
useful to recognize that this is not a new... that\h
the development of the context is not a new thing.\h\h
It's something that you've already been doing\h
all the time. It's just more often than not the\h\h
wrong kind of context. So the context of,
like\hI said, finding pleasure in sensuality,\h\h
resisting the unpleasant, that's another context\h
that's pretty much by default there. And then if\h\h
you don't question it and you just go about\h
your day as an ordinary person, you will be\h\h
cultivating that context. And distraction is to\h
cultivate the context of ignorance. Exactly. Yes.\h\h
So that's another one that's...
You\hdon't need to make any effort. It's going to be\h\h
there by itself just because that's the starting\h
point of an ignorant mind. So then if you don't\h\h
make an effort to... That's why it's so important to\h
question the motivation behind your actions which\h\h
doesn't, as we've often clarified, is not about\h
a reason that you can kind of explain at\h\h
arms length. It's at that emotional level, which\h
means you need to ask yourself, you need to\h\h
uncover the motivation that's already there.\h
Not like you choose the motivation;
rather if you look you will see there is some\h
kind of force that's driving you to do X or Y\h\h
and that's where you would be able to see: Oh\h
is there a context of wanting to, like you\h\h
said, distraction; or wanting to turn away from\h
the neutral feeling of not much going on.
Well, that's a context that would be there enduring\h
on its own. And by overlooking it, you're\h
acting out of it and you're making it even more...\h
you're taking yourself even farther away from\h\h
the wholesome context of non-distraction.
Or from\hrecognizing any context whatsoever.
Exactly. Yes, because that's the other problem with
the context\hof the unwholesome ones; the context of\h\h
greed, aversion, and delusion; of sensuality,\h
ill will, cruelty. It's that they...\h
you can't mindfully cultivate that context. In other words,\h
you can't mindfully engage in sensuality,\h\h
mindfully engage in ill will, mindfully engage in\h
cruelty, mindfully engage in destruction. That's a\h\h
contradiction in terms. So you would\h
then realize that: Well, that's pretty much the\h\h
primary harm of these things. Even if I don't\hsee
an immediate harm from it yet,\h\h
the simple fact that it obstructs your\h
self-awareness means like it's pretty\h\h
much like taking an intoxicant. Like, you don't\h
know what you're going to end up doing if you\h\h
take enough of an intoxicating substance.\h
Well, it's the same thing. And actually\h\h
the Buddha called it intoxication, and
one of the translations for this term\h\h
that's often rendered as heedfulness is non-\h
intoxication,  appamāda, which is exactly what you\h\h
will be cultivating. You would realize your\h
normal context, your normal state of being,
is one of intoxication with one thing or the other.\h
It doesn't necessarily have to be full-on coarse\h
sensual pleasure. You're just intoxicated with\h–
in the broadest sense – life as such; with\h\h
your ambitions, your goals, the things that\h
you value. Your health, protecting your health\h\h
for its own sake, not even for the\h
sake of practice, but just because you resist\h\h
illness as such. Intoxication with youth, as if,
you know, it were ultimately in your\hcontrol.
Yes. Or like: "I can do it because I'm\h
still young and even if it goes wrong, I have\h\h
time in the future to correct my mistakes", which\h
is all based on assumptions that are dangerous.\h\h
Yes. And also, even if you don't have\h
something that fits neatly in one of\h\h
those three categories, well ultimately you will be\h
intoxicated with some sight, sound, smell, taste,\h\h
touch or even mental image. So you might have even\h
ideas about the practice and they might be right ideas,
but you often see that how somebody\h
could become so engaged on that level\h\h
of mental figuring out and intellectualizing, that\h
that becomes pretty much their way of scratching\hthe itch;
their way of cultivating the same\h
context of unwholesome kind of seeking\h\h
gratification at the wrong place. It would\h
be fed through that same... because that\h
is the context that you're already following,\h
that's already driving you to act in such ways,\h\h
well, the more you act in such ways, the more\h
you will be strengthening that context.
It's like a bully. The more you allow him to tell\h
you what to do and harass you and you don't\h\h
push back against it, the more he will be doing\hit.
Now earlier you said that you cannot mindfully\h\h
engage in sensuality. That that's a contradiction.\h
That acting out of sensuality by definition means\h\h
that you've lost the perspective. Yes. Does that\h
mean that the pleasure of sensual pleasures is a\h\h
memory? Like, you indulge, which means that\h
you've basically lost the perspective and\h\h
at some point you sort of come out of it and then\h
you say – wrongly – that is what was pleasant. So in a\h\h
sense the pleasure is a sort of a recollection;\h
you're not actually...
Well, if you were... it's always with reference to\h
either the past or the future, because you\h\h
can't really be enjoying... When you look\h
at the sensual state of mind, it's never about\h\h
what you're getting now; it's about the next\h
pump of pleasure that would come. So it's
in a way, yes, it's always either\h
a memory or something that you anticipate.